<intro-section>
<quote>The living thing did I follow; I walked in the broadest and narrowest paths to learn its nature.<br/>

With a hundred-faced mirror did I catch its glance when its mouth was shut, so that its eye might speak unto me. And its eye spake unto me.<br/>

Friedrich Nietzsche</quote>

<quote>Destroy the mind, destroy the body, but you cannot destroy the heart<br/>

The Smashing Pumpkins</quote>

<p>This work was a challenge to bring to fruition. I was supported and encouraged by many people and I thank them all. While it is impossible list everyone who assisted me, I will mention of a few special people.</p>

<p>To my immediate research team: Andy, Brian, Dumebi, Helen, James, Karel, Liam, Matt, Matt, Nico, Phil, Segun, Simon and Stephen, thanks for our many discussions on technical matters, current affairs and for good times. Also, I am very grateful for the friendship and encouragement of Ash. My research was initiated from the EPSRC funded LiLiR project and I want to extend my gratitude to Richard, Stephen, Barry, Gari, Yuxuan, Jake and Sarah for their useful input and providing direction to this work. I also wish to thank the university staff who assisted this work, particularly Bevis King, James Field, Liz James, Dawn Duke and Shane Dowle.</p>

<p>Thanks goes to my family and particularly to my parents for providing support that cannot be measured. Also, thanks to my old friends (you know who you are, I hope) and new friends Martin, Cemre, Stuart, Rui, Iris, Phil for providing a spot of sunshine. Many professionals helped me keep mind and body together; special thanks to Chris Powell, Philip Bull, Duncan Sellers, Nicole Muller, Dee Ainsworth and Brenda Dilks for your timely help.</p>

<p>Many thanks to Rich Bowden for giving me the opportunity to do research, for providing copious guidance for my own good (most of which I followed) and particularly for how to best communicate my research. His support, persistence and patience during my active work and during my absences was invaluable. Eng-Jon Ong was my scientific guru for the past 5 years and this work would have been impossible without his help.</p>

</intro-section>

